<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>O'Reilly on Sevim Cengiz</title><link>https://sevimcengiz.github.io/tags/OReilly/</link><description>Recent content in O'Reilly on Sevim Cengiz</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sevimcengiz.github.io/tags/OReilly/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fundamentals of Data Visualization</title><link>https://sevimcengiz.github.io/blog/2018/01/23/fundamentals-of-data-visualization/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sevimcengiz.github.io/blog/2018/01/23/fundamentals-of-data-visualization/</guid><description>
&lt;script src="https://sevimcengiz.github.io/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;p>I’m very excited to announce my latest project, a book on data visualization. The working title is “Fundamentals of Data Visualization”. The book will be published with O’Reilly, and a preview is &lt;a href="https://clauswilke.com/dataviz/">available here.&lt;/a> The entire book is written in R Markdown, and the figures are made with ggplot2. The source for the book is &lt;a href="https://github.com/clauswilke/dataviz">available on github.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even though the entire book is written in R Markdown, it is not a book on programming. The book is meant as a guide to making visualizations that accurately reflect the data, tell a story, and look professional. It has grown out of my experience of working with students and postdocs in my laboratory on thousands of data visualizations. Over the years, I have noticed that the same issues arise over and over. I have attempted to collect my accumulated knowledge from these interactions in the form of this book.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As of this writing, approximately half of the planned chapters are completed, and all completed chapters are available online. I will post future chapters as they become available. Since this is a work in progress, not everything may be completely finalized, and I may rewrite some of the posted chapters at a later date. I welcome feedback. If you see any errors or other problems, please &lt;a href="https://github.com/clauswilke/dataviz/issues">open an issue on github.&lt;/a> If you have suggestions for other topics to cover, or for datasets that would work well for certain chapters, please also feel free to record these suggestions as issues on github.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With very few exceptions, all figures in the book are generated straight from ggplot2, with no manual post-processing in photoshop or illustrator. (At present, the only exception is two figures in the chapter on &lt;a href="https://clauswilke.com/dataviz/image-file-formats.html">image file formats.&lt;/a>) Therefore, the book also serves as a showcase of what ggplot2 can do. I am using the bleeding edge of ggplot2 software development, though. To reproduce all the figures in the book, you may have to install current development versions of several R packages.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>